Chapter 107.
The Carpenter.
Seat thyself sultanically among the moons of Saturn, and take high
abstracted man alone, and he seems a wonder, a grandeur, and a woe. but from
the same point take mankind in mass, and for the most part they seem a mob of
unnecessary duplicates, both contemporary and hereditary.
But most humble though he was, and far from furnishing an example of the high
humane abstraction, the Peekquad's carpenter was no duplicate, hence he now
comes in person on this stage.
Like all seagoing ship carpenters, and more especially those belonging to
whailing vessels, he was to a certain off-handed practical extent, alike
experienced in numerous trades and callings collateral to his own, the
carpenter's pursuit being the ancient and outbranching trunk of all those
numerous handiccrafts which more or less have to do with wood as an auxiliary
material. But besides the application to him of the generic remark above, this
carpenter of the Pequad was singularly efficient in those thousand nameless
mechanical emergencies continually recurring in a large ship upon a three
or four years voyage in univilized and faristant seas. for not to speak of his
readiness in ordinary duties, repairing stove boats, sprung spars, reforming the
shape of clumsy bladed ores, inserting bull's eyes in the deck, or new tree
nails in the side planks, and other miscellaneous matters more directly
pertaining to his special business. He was, moreover, unhesitatingly expert in
all manner of conflicting aptitudes, both useful and capriccious.
The one grand stage where he enacted all his various parts, so manifold, was his
vice bench, a long, rude, ponderous table furnished with several vices, of
different sizes, and both of iron and of wood. At all times, except when whales
were alongside, this bench was securely lashed at thwart ships, against the rear
of the triworks.
A bellaying pin is found too large to be easily inserted into its hole. The
carpenter claps it into one of his ever ready vices and straightway files it
smaller. A lost landird of strange plumage strays on board and is made a
captive. Out of clean shaved rods of right whale bone and cross beams of
sperm whale ivory, the carpenter makes a pagod looking cage for it. An orsman
sprains his wrist. The carpenter concocts a soothing lotion. Stub longed
for vermilion stars to be painted upon the blade of his every ore. Screwing
each ore in his big vice of wood, the carpenter symmetrically supplies the
constellation. A sailor takes a fancy to wear sharp bone earrings. The carpenter
drills his ears. Another has a toothache. The carpenter out pincers,
and clapping one hand upon his bench, bids him be seated there. But the poor
fellow unmanageably winces under the unconcluded operation. Whirling round
the handle of his wooden vice, the carpenter signs him to clap his jaw in
that if he would have him draw the tooth.
Thus this carpenter was prepared at all points and alike indifferent and without
respect in all. Teeth he accounted bits of ivory, heads he deemed but top
blocks, men themselves he lightly held for capstands. But while now, upon so
wide a field, thus variously accomplished, and with such liveless of
expertness in him, too, all this would seem to argue some uncommon vivacity of intelligence.
But not precisely so. For nothing was this man more remarkable than for a
certain impersonal stalidity, as it were, impersonal, I say, for it so
shaded off into the surrounding infinite of things, that it seemed one with the
general stallity discernable in the whole visible world, which while
pauselessly active in uncounted modes, still eternally holds its peace, and
ignores you, though you dig foundations for cathedrals. Yet was this halfh
horrible stalidity in him, involving too, as it appeared, an all rammifying
heartlessness, yet was it oddly dashed at times, with an old crutch-like
antid-oluvian wheezing humorousness, not unstreked now and then with a certain
grizzled wittiness, such as might have served to pass the time during the
midnight watch on the bearded folk of Noah's ark. Was it that this old
carpenter had been a lifelong wanderer, whose much rolling to and fro not only
had gathered no moss, but what is more had rubbed off whatever small outward
clings might have originally pertained to him? He was a stripped abstract, an
unfractioned integral, uncompromised as a newborn babe, living without
premeditated reference to this world or the next. You might almost say that this
strange uncompromisedness in him involved a sort of unintelligence.
For in his numerous trades he did not seem to work so much by reason or by
instinct or simply because he had been tutored to it or by any intermixture of
all these, even or uneven, but merely by a kind of deaf and dumb spontaneous
literal process. He was a pure manipulator. His brain, if he had ever
had one, must have early oozed along into the muscles of his fingers. He was
like one of those unreasoning but still highly useful moltum imparvo Sheffield
contrivances, assuming the exterior, though a little swelled, of a common
pocketk knife, but containing not only blades of various sizes, but also
screwdrivers, corkcrews, tweezers, alls, pens, rulers, nail filers, counter
sinkers. So if his superiors wanted to use the carpenter for a screwdriver, all
they had to do was to open that part of
him, and the screw was fast, or if for tweezers, take him up by the legs, and
there they were.
Yet, as previously hinted, this omni toolled openshot carpenter was, after
all, no mere machine of an automaton. If he did not have a common soul in him, he
had a subtle something that somehow anomalously did its duty. What that was,
whether essence of quicks or a few drops of heartsorn, there was no telling. But
there it was, and there it had abided for now some 60 years or more. And this
it was this same unaccountable cunning life principle in him. This it was that
kept him a great part of the time saliloquising but only like an unreasoning wheel which
also hummingly saliloquises.
Or rather his body was a sentry box and this saliloquiser on guard there and
talking all the time to keep himself awake.